Library Company of Philadelphia publications LCP.Publications
Library Company of Philadelphia
The resurgent feeling that "something should be done" had been repressed during the 1930s and 1940s because the financial difficulties of the Library Company precluded any constructive change. Edwin Wolf 2nd was engaged to make a survey of the collections, to assess their scope, size, and importance, and to suggest means to improve their care and usefulness. Then, four eminent librarians - Lloyd A. Brown of the Peabody Institute, William A. Jackson of Harvard, Paul North Rice of the New York Public Library, and Clifford K. Shipton of the American Antiquarian Society - were invited to inspect the Library Company and consult with the directors about its future.
Unanimously, the experts agreed that the Library Company's greatest strength lay in its rare books and manuscripts, and that its greatest contribution to society would be as a scholarly research library with special emphasis on American history and culture. There was no doubt that the rare books and manuscripts were far more numerous and more valuable than had been generally believed. The first and immediate step the consultants urged was a program of rehabilitation. The most valuable books should be taken from the scattered locations, recatalogued, repaired, and temporarily reshelved in a room to be refitted and air-conditioned. Then the experts recommended that the Library Company reduce and refine its mass of late-nineteenth- and twentieth-century books, keeping only those which would supplement as reference works the basic historical collections.
These steps were, however, considered preliminary to a decision to move out of the Ridgway Library. That structure, once considered fireproof, was judged instead to be a fire-trap. Furthermore, the roof leaked, the basement was damp, and the building's location in the city was unfortunate. The consensus was that the Library Company should move to modern quarters in or adjacent to another compatible library as soon as possible.
By 1955, with income from the parking garage increasing, the Library Company could stand on its own feet. In December of that year, the arrangement with the Free Library was amicably terminated. Wolf became Librarian. He shared the excitement of rediscovery and revitalization with an audience of bookmen - librarians, collectors, booksellers, and, of course, members of the Library Company - through his paradoxically light yet scholarly essays in the Annual Reports.
The experts' primary recommendation - to move from the totally inadequate and unsuitable Ridgway Library - had not been forgotten. A location next to the Historical Society was favored. The steps necessary to bring the plan to fruition were interlocking and complicated. Fortunately, at the critical time the City of Philadelphia made a satisfactory offer for the building and land. The Library Company was given permission to make the sale and also to use such other funds as were part of the Rush estate to build the new library. Three nineteenth-century brownstone houses, owned by and contiguous to the Historical Society, were purchased and torn down. Plans for a modern eight-story building were drawn by the architectural firm of Carroll, Grisdale, and Van Alen, and construction began in 1964. Meanwhile, in order to carry out another of the original recommendations concerning the future of the Library Company and to avoid moving unwanted books, a sweep of the shelves was undertaken. With formal authorization from the directors and the membership as a whole, Wolf culled and disposed of such works printed after 1880 as were deemed not germane to the Library Company's main collections.
With the Library Company's holdings down to an estimated 375,000 volumes, the Library Company was ready to return to the center of the city. The new building was completed by the end of 1965. The difficult transfer of the books nevertheless provided an opportunity to revamp the shelving arrangement and gather together subject classes which the space problems in the old building had fragmented. Because approximately two-thirds of the funds for the new library derived from the Rush estate, the building, like its predecessor, was named the Ridgway Library. The building was opened to the public in April 1966. A reciprocal arrangement was reached with the neighboring Historical Society whereby its rare books are shelved and used by readers in the Library Company, and the latter's manuscripts are shelved and used by readers in the Historical Society.
An interest in eighteenth-century intellectual history led Wolf in 1956 to begin the reconstruction of three colonial private libraries which had been partly or wholly incorporated into the Library Company - those of James Logan, Benjamin Franklin, and William Byrd of Westover, Virginia. He published a definitive catalogue of Logan's library in 1974. The other two libraries had been scattered by 1800, but he was able to locate substantial parts of them on the Library Company's shelves and in other collections across the country.
Comparing the Library Company's holdings with already-published subject bibliographies uncovered still more collections of surprising strength in areas such as technology, Judaica, household and cookery books, courtesy books, gift books, and architecture. In the process of strengthening and extending the Library Company's core collection, unnecessary or expensive duplication of the holdings of other local libraries was always avoided. This principle was applied not only to individual books but to whole areas of collecting. All acquisitions still build on the core collection acquired between 1731 and 1880. The collection is constantly growing, but its essential character has not changed.
The move to the new Ridgway Library proved fruitful for the print collection of the Library Company as well. With the appointment of Stefanie A. Munsing as curator of prints in 1971, the Print Department was born and quickly became a center of activity. A vast task faced the new curator of reorganizing and cataloguing the accumulation of Philadelphia views, portraits, American political cartoons, and early photographs. In 1975, Bernard Reilly moved from the Reading Room to the Print Department. It was during his tenure and due to his initiative that the Library Company's remarkable collection of nineteenth-century Philadelphia photographs began to be appreciated.
In 1977, Kenneth Finkel took over the Print Department. Under his aggressive and imaginative curatorship from 1977 to 1994, the collection increased at a phenomenal rate. With the exhibition and simultaneous publication in 1980 of Nineteenth-Century Photography in Philadelphia, the Print Department became the center for the study of early photography in Philadelphia.
Conservation of the ever-growing collections grew in importance over the years. A bindery was first set up at the Library Company in 1954 by the German master bookbinder Fritz Eberhardt to repair and rebind in chronological order the vast collection of pamphlet Americana. After Eberhardt left in 1957, Kaspar Reder was hired to continue the work. The care of the print collection was taken up in 1971 with the bindery staff working under the guidance of Curator of Prints Stefanie Munsing. Under Chief of Conservation Jennifer Woods Rosner, the staff began to move systematically through the entire rare book collection, and its range of treatments has widened to include making protective boxes, reattaching covers detached from leather bindings, repairing cloth bindings of the 19th century, and replacing old library bindings with new ones made of high-quality archival materials.
Under the direction of Librarian Wolf, the Library Company assumed a leading role in the cultural and intellectual community of Philadelphia and established a reputation of scholarly service both locally and internationally. Franklinian common sense, with a dash of thrift, was its guide, as befit a library struggling to be reborn. Wolf retired at the end of 1984 and was succeeded by John C. Van Horne, who came to the Library Company from the American Philosophical Society. Under Van Horne's guidance the Library Company struck out in several new directions. The Library Company began to attract more scholars to the collections by instituting an endowed research fellowship program in 1987 that provides modest stipends to enable graduate students and senior scholars to travel to Philadelphia to conduct research at the Library Company. The Library Company also created a revolving Publication Fund that supports the publication of a variety of works, usually carrying the joint imprint of the Library Company and a commercial or university press co-publisher. These books are generally based on the collections or relate to special projects or programs.
In the second half of the twentieth century, the Library Company has been utterly transformed from a dusty mausoleum filled with books that were deteriorating from heat, damp, and dust, to a busy and vital center for research and education of national importance. The Library Company remains open and free of charge to any serious scholar, but the collections are now housed in closed stacks, and no rare materials circulate except as loans for exhibition in other institutions. The collections are constantly and vigorously expanded and enriched, and they are fully accessible through card catalogues and other in-house finding aids.
All these changes have been made in order to carry out the Library Company's new mission as articulated in the 1950s: to collect, preserve, and make available books, graphics, and other primary source materials for the study of American history and culture up to the closing years of the 19th century. Much has changed and will change, but one thing remains constant: the collections are the focus of all the library's energies, and the reason for its existence.
Bibliography:
Quoted directly, in segments from: At the Instance of Benjamin Franklin: A Brief History of The Library Company of Philadelphia, 1995 [full document available at: http://librarycompany.org/about/Instance.pdf]
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research use, on deposit at the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, 1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA 19107. For access, please contact the Historical Society at 215-732-6200 or visit http://www.hsp.org.
Scope and Contents note
This collection consists of printed material created by the Library Company of Philadelphia. Included are brochures; information about institutional resources and services; event brochures, announcements, exhibit catalogues, and conference programs; and published works regarding the Library Company of Philadelphia or the materials held by the Library Company of Philadelphia.
This collection is arranged into four series: "About the Library Company of Philadelphia," "Events," "Published Works," and "James Rush works." Material within the "About the Library Company of Philadelphia," series includes a sampling of brochures that address topics such as: general information and history of the Library Company of Philadelphia, information about construction, preservation of materials and the building, and planned giving; fellowship opportunities; and the Library Company's involvement with other organizations, such as Independent Research Libraries Association and Philadelphia Area Consortium of Special Collections Libraries. Also included are two publications that focused on the Library Company: the Renaissance Library calendar and an entire issue of the magazine Antiques. These materials are arranged chronologically.
"Events" includes announcement brochures, invitations, programs, and exhibit catalogues for events held at the Library Company of Philadelphia, benefitting the Library Company of Philadelphia, or associated with the Library Company of Philadelphia. This series provides a glimpse into the types of collections housed at the Library Company as well as the ways in which the Library Company interprets its collections and its history. Events include exhibits, symposia, lectures, conferences, and benefits on topics such as early American economics, food history, the temperance movement, and the history of libraries, to name only a few. These materials are arranged chronologically.
The "Published works" series includes materials that were actually published by the Library Company of Philadelphia. These materials are often about the Library Company, in particular: Charter Members of the Library Company, At the Instance of Benjamin Franklin, and Quarter of a Millennium: The Library Company of Philadelphia, 1731-1981. Others focus on the collections of the Library Company and these include writings on Commodore Thomas Truxtun, photographs and prints, and the musical works of William Henry Fry. Finally, there are some publications more broadly about Philadelphia.
The "James Rush works" were not published by the Library Company, but copyright now belongs to them. James Rush, in his will, states, “I have given the copyrights of all my works to the Library Company, and I will and direct that they shall for the next half century, publish every ten years (and earlier and oftener if called for) an edition of five hundred copies of any or all of them, so that they shall always have on hand a number sufficient to supply any demand which may be made for any or either of them, at a price not exceeding the cost of publication.” Included are all the published works by Rush.
Finkel, Kenneth; Library Company of Philadelphia.; Rush, James, 1786-1869; Wolf, Edwin, 1911-1991; Brochures; Exhibition catalogs; Libraries; Pennsylvania--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Philadelphia (Pa.); Publications; Research libraries; Subscription libraries; United States--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775
- Series I. About the Library Company
  - Construction, preservation and planned giving brochures, circa 1992, undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures, 1995, 2000, undated (Box 1)
  - Fellowship brochures, 1997-2000 (Box 1)
  - Antiques, "The Library Company of Philadelphia", 2006 August (Box 1)
  - Renaissance Library calendar, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Independent Research Libraries Association brochure, undated (Box 1)
  - Philadelphia Area Consortium of Special Collections Libraries (PACSCL) brochure and "Leaves of Gold" cd-rom, undated (Box 1)
- Series II. Events
  - "Exhibition of Books and Manuscripts in Commemoration of the 150th Anniversary of the signing of the Constitution of the United States, September 17, 1787," exhibition catalog, 1937 July 4-October 15 (Box 1)
  - "Christmas Books, 1524-1938," exhibition catalog, 1938 December 19-1939 January 31 (Box 1)
  - "American Fine Printing, 1820-1880," exhibition catalog, 1979 October-1980 January (Box 1)
  - "Quarter of A Millennium, 1731-1981," brochures, program and book awards (Box 1)
  - "First American Editions," exhibition catalog, 1986 March 2-June 29 (Box 1)
  - "The Larder Invaded: Three Centuries of Philadelphia Food," brochure, 1986 November 18-1987 April 25 (Box 1)
  - "Legacies of Genius: A Celebration of Philadelphia Libraries," press packet, 1988 April-September (Box 1)
  - "We Abolition Women are Turning the World Upside Down!" exhibition catalog, 1989 March-June (Box 1)
  - "Poor Richard's Books," exhibit invitation, 1990 April 18 (Box 1)
  - "A Walk on the Wild Side: The Wissahickon Creek, 1800 to 1940," exhibition announcement and catalog, 1993 October 18-1994 March 18 (Box 1)
  - Annual Meeting, invitations, 1994, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - "William Mackenzie: America's First Rare Book Collector," exhibition checklist and lecture announcement for "Bibliophily in the Age of William Mackenzie," by Paul Needham, 1994 November 9-1995 March 24 (Box 1)
  - "Delightful Doings and Breathless Bidding," invitation and auction catalog, 1997 April 4 (Box 1)
  - "Open House," invitation, 1998 March 13 (Box 1)
  - Fall Programs, brochure, 1998 (Box 1)
  - "Ardent Spirits: The Origins of the American Temperance Movement," brochures, 1999 April 19-November 24 (Box 1)
  - "Open Houses," invitations, 2000 March 17 (Box 1)
  - "The Genesis of Republicanism: The Birth and Growth of the Grand Old Party," symposium program and exhibit brochures, 2000 June 14-December 1 (Box 1)
  - "The Hook and the Book: the Emergence of Crochet and Knitting in American Popular Culture, 1840-1876," exhibition announcement and catalog, 2001 January 22-September 28 (Box 1)
  - "History of Libraries in the United States," conference brochure, 2002 April 11-13 (Box 1)
  - "Risk and Reputation: Insecurity in the Early American Economy," conference program, 2002 October 4 (Box 1)
  - "The Atlantic Economy in the Era of 18th Century Revolutions," conference program, 2003 September 19 (Box 1)
  - "Picturing Women," brochure, 2004 January-May (Box 1)
  - "From the Bottom Up: Popular Reading and Writing in the Michael Zinman Collection of Early American Imprints," exhibition catalog, 2004 May 25-December 17 (Box 1)
  - "Conference on Health and Medicine in the Era of Lewis and Clark," Francis Clark Wood Institute for the History of Medicine conference program, 2004 November 4-6 (Box 1)
  - "Intersections: Scriptures, Prints and Paintings in Antebellum America," exhibition brochures, 2005 January 24-July 22 (Box 1)
  - "Ephemera Across the Atlantic: Popular Print Culture in Two Worlds," symposium program, 2005 September 15-17 (Box 1)
  - "Connection, Contingency, and Class in the Early Republic's Economy," conference program, 2005 October 28 (Box 1)
  - "Beau Tie Bash: A Benefit for the Library Company of Philadelphia," invitation from the Freeman's Auction House, 2005 November 12 (Box 1)
  - "Ben Franklin 300," official guide and exhibition brochure for National Constitution Center, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  - "'All Sorts of Printing at reasonable Rates': Franklin's Way to Wealth as a Job Printer," invitation to illustrated talk by James Green, Librarian, 2006 September 14 (Box 1)
  - "In Good Company: The Library Company of Philadelphia's 275th Anniversary," save the date and invitation, 2006 November 8 (Box 1)
  - "Black Voices, from the Shelves of the Library Company," exhibition catalog, undated (Box 1)
  - Holiday Party, invitation, undated (Box 1)
- Series III. Published works
  - Catalog of the Books belonging to the Loganian Library, and First Supplement, 1837, 1867 (Box 2)
  - Charter Members of the Library Company, by Francis R. Packard, M.D., 1942 March 25 (Box 2)
  - On the Improvement and Settlement of Lands in the United States, an essay by the late James Wilson, 1946 (Box 2)
  - The Musical Works of William Henry Fry in the collections of the Library Company of Philadelphia, by William Treat Upton, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Commodore Thomas Truxtun, 1755-1822: A Description of the Truxtun-Biddle Letters in the collections of the Library Company of Philadelphia, by Eugene S. Ferguson, 1947 (Box 2)
  - The First Books and Printed Catalogues of the Library Company of Philadelphia, by Edwin Wolf, 2nd, 1954 (Box 2)
  - A Check-List of the Books in the Library Company of Philadelphia in and supplementary to Wing's Short-Title Catalogue, 1641-1700, by Edwin Wolf, 2nd, 1959 (Volume 1-10)
  - American Song Sheets, Slip Ballads, and Poetical Broadsides, 1850-1870: A Catalogue of the Collection of the Library Company of Philadelphia, by Edwin Wolf, 2nd, 1963 (Volume 11-14)
  - Bibliothesauri: or Jewels from the Shelves of the Library Company of Philadelphia, being a catalogue of a selection of Rare, Old, Curious, Valuable, Important, Unusual, Beautiful, Influential, and Historic books in the fields of Religion, Law, Science, Medicine, History, Travel, Art and Literature, by Edwin Wolf, 2nd, 1966 (Volume 15-16)
  - Journal of the Proceedings of the Congress held at Philadelphia, September 5, 1774: A facsimile of the official edition printed in 1774, with an introduction by Edwin Wolf, 2nd, 1974 (Volume 17-18)
  - The Library of James Logan of Philadelphia, 1674-1751, by Edwin Wolf, 2nd, 1974 (Volume 19)
  - "At the Instance of Benjamin Franklin": A Brief History of the Library Company of Philadelphia, 1731-1976, by Edwin Wolf, 2nd (Volume 20-25)
  - Nineteenth Century Photography in Philadelphia: 250 Historic Prints from the Library Company of Philadelphia, by Kenneth Finkel, 1980 (Volume 26-31)
  - Quarter of a Millennium: The Library Company of Philadelphia, 1731-1981, by Edwin Wolf, 2nd (dummy and copy) (Volume 32-33)
  - Legacy in Ice: The Vaux Family and the Canadian Alps, by Edward Cavell, 1983 (Volume 34)
  - Legacies of Genius: A Celebration of Philadelphia Libraries, 1988 (Volume 35)
  - Philadelphia Then and Now: 60 Sites Photographed in the Past and Present, by Kenneth Finkel and Susan Oyama, 1988 (Volume 36)
  - Philadelphia: Portrait of an American City, by Edwin Wolf, 2nd, 1990 (Volume 37-38)
  - From Gothic Windows to Peacocks: American Embossed Leather Bindings, 1825-1855, by Edwin Wolf, 2nd, 1990 (Volume 39-40)
  - Edwin Wolf 2nd, 1911-1991: An Autobiographical Sketch written in 1987 and a Bibliography of the Published Writings of Edwin Wolf 2nd (Volume 41)
  - Anthony Garvin: Culture, History, and Artifacts, Memorial Tribute, by Murray G. Murphey, 1992 (Volume 42)
  - Philadelphia Almanac and Citizens' Manual, edited by Kenneth Finkel, 1994 (Volume 43)
  - Philadelphia Almanac and Citizens' Manual, edited by Kenneth Finkel, 1995 (Volume 44)
  - The Michael Zinman Collection of Early American Imprints, by William S. Reese and James Green, 2001 (Volume 45-46)
- Series IV. James Rush works
  - Hamlet, A Dramatic Prelude; in Five Acts, 1834 (Volume 47-48)
  - Brief Outline of an Analysis of the Human Intellect; intended to Rectify the Scholastic and Vulgar Perversions of the Natural Purpose and Method of Thinking by rejecting altogether the Theoretic Confusion, the Unmeaning Arrangement, and Indefinite Nomenclature of the Metaphysician, 1865 (Volume 49-50)
  - Rhymes of Contrast on Wisdom and Folly. A Comparison between Observant and Reflective Age, derisively called fogie, and a Senseless and Unthinking American Go-Ahead, intended to exemplify and Important Agent in the Working Plan of the Human Intellect: A Narrated Dialogue, 1869 (Volume 51)
  - The Philosophy of the Human Voice: Embracing its Physiological History; together with a System of Principles by which Criticism in the Art of Elocution may be rendered intelligible, and Instruction, Definitive and Comprehensive to Which is added a Brief Analysis of Song and Recitative, 1900 (Volume 52)